let a and b be two positive real numbers
and consider line segments of length a
and b
use these two line segments to create a
circle of diameter a
and a circle of diameter b
then move these two circles together so
that they are tangent
the lengths of the radii of the two
circles are a over two and b over two so
the length of the line segment
connecting the centers of the two
circles is given by the sum a plus b
over two the horizontal line coming from
the center of the smaller circle and
intersecting the diameter of the larger
circle creates a line segment of length
absolute value of a minus b over 2. to
find the length of the line segment that
we just drew that represents the
distance between the x-coordinates of
the centers of the circle we can use the
pythagorean theorem since it forms one
leg of a right triangle
the square of a plus b over two minus
the square of the absolute value of a
minus b over two is equal to the
quantity a times b so the desired length
is the square root of a times b
but then from this diagram we can see
that the value a plus b over 2 which is
the hypotenuse of a right triangle is
greater than or equal to the square root
of a times b which is the length of a
leg of the same right triangle no matter
how we change the sizes of a and b we
see that a plus b over 2 is always the
hypotenuse and square root of a b is
always the leg of a right triangle
they only become equal if a and b are
exactly the same so we see that a plus b
over 2 is equal to the square root of a
b if and only if a equals b the
inequality that we've just proved using
this circle diagram is called the
arithmetic mean geometric mean
inequality
you